<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="object_names">
        <item>Sassi-Jaani farm</item>
        <item>Köstriaseme farm</item>
        <item>Nuki farm</item>
        <item>Nätsi windmill</item>
        <item>Härjapea farm</item>
        <item>Pulga farm</item>
        <item>Aarte farm</item>
        <item>Kahala watermill</item>
        <item>Sepa farm</item>
        <item>Kalma windmill</item>
        <item>Ritsu farm</item>
        <item>Rusi farm</item>
        <item>Setu farm</item>
        <item>Russian house from Peipus</item>
        <item>Jaagu farm</item>
        <item>Jüri-Jaagu farm</item>
        <item>Kolga farm</item>
        <item>Roosta farm</item>
        <item>Moravian church prayer house</item>
        <item>Hiiuma itinerant fishing house</item>
        <item>Net sheds</item>
        <item>Windmills</item>
        <item>Sutlepa chapel</item>
        <item>Lau village shop</item>
        <item>Orgmetsa fire station</item>
        <item>Kuie school building</item>
        <item>Kolu inn</item>
    </string-array>
    
    <string-array name="object_descriptions">
        <item>"The farm is from Kullamaa parish in the early 19th C. The buildings were brought to the museum in 1959-1960 and opened to visitors in 1964. The threshing house and storehouse burned in 1984. The restored farm was re-opened at the museum in 1993."</item>
        <item>"Köstriaseme farm is from Kirikla village in Hageri parish. The buildings were brought to the museum from 1959-1962, and the farmyard was opened to visitors in 1962."</item>
        <item>"Nuki smokehouse is an example of the yard of a poorer inhabitant of western Estonia on the periphery of the farm. Built in 1880-1890 at the former site of the Nuki cotter in Saunja village in Lääne-Nigula parish. Brought to the museum in 1970, erected from 1970-1971."</item>
    	<item>"Big post windmill comes from Vanasauna farm in Nätsi village, Mihkli parish, the southern part of Läänemaa County in Western Estonia. Allegedly, it was built in the second half of the 19th century on Pärdi-Madise farm in Rabivere village, Hageri parish and was then sold to Nätsi village in Mihkli parish. The windmill was owned by different farms in the course of time, until Ants Kümmel, a cotter from Vanasauna farm, bought it after the First World War. He enlarged the windmill and started to grind flour for villages in the neighbourhood. The windmill was transferred to the museum in 1959 and opened in 1960. "</item>
    	<item>"This average-sized Viru County farm was purchased from the owners of Mäetaguse manor for 4,000 silver roubles in 1892. The farm had 44 ha of land, including 13 ha of fields.\n\nSimilarly to what people did elsewhere in Viru County, the family of Härjapea farm earned money to raise the amount payable and to build the new dwelling by selling their produce on Saint Petersburg markets. The dwelling constructed during the Empire era was later modernised, and the rooms show people’s life at the end of 1930s. The orchard and flower beds are also characteristic of the household culture of the first Republic of Estonia. The farm homestead features the outbuildings of Kutsari farm dating back to the end of the 19th century and the stone threshing floor of a ruined barn-dwelling, so the composite name of ‘Kutsari- Härjapea’ is also in use. The sauna is located farther away at the pond."</item>
    	<item>"Pulga farm represents a rental farm characteristic of Northern Estonia and dating back to the middle of the 19th century. Farm buildings were brought from the villages of Kuusalu parish. The buildings were brought to the museum in 1961–1964, and the farmyard was opened to visitors in 1964. The fact that soil in Northern Estonia is rich in limestone is displayed by many buildings located in the spacious yard: the threshing floor of the barn-dwelling, the smithy and summer kitchen are all made of limestone. Stone hedges where large slabs of stone alternate with stonework catch the eye as well.\n\nA family story related to Pulga hereditary farm dates back as far as to the 18th century. It is in 1837 that the parish register first mentioned the surname of Konton, the family living on Pulga farm. It is also engraved on the plate on the threshing floor wall, which tells us the name of the barn-dwelling builder and the year of construction: “1860 JUHAN KONTON”. Later, Juhan’s son built a more modern dwelling next to the barn-dwelling. The farmers paid the rent to Kolga manor. They had little field land, merely 4.5 ha, and draught oxen (which were also for sale) were used for ploughing up to 1930s. It was only in 1905 that Kolga manor sold farms as freehold."</item>
    	<item>"Aarte farm is an example of a small farm belonging to a fisherman in the 2nd half of the 19th century. Farm buildings have been brought from Aarte farm in Virve village on Juminda peninsula, Kuusalu parish. The farm was opened for visitors in 1982.\n\nThe fisherman’s family only had 3–4 ha of land where it grew potatoes and vegetables. It got grain for making bread from inland farms in exchange for fish. Fishing was the main source of income, and more could be earned by serving on ships and working in construction. The fishermen inhabiting the villages along the coast of the Gulf of Finland had close contact with the Finns for centuries because owning a boat was much more common than having a horse. This is why their language and culture adopted numerous Finnish traits.\n\nFishermen’s lifestyle changed for the better in 1870s, when coastal trade expanded mainly because potatoes were taken for sale to Saint Petersburg and to Finland."</item>
    	<item>"The small watermill built on Liiva spring on Möldri farm in Kahala village, Kuusalu parish, was used to grind straight flour, wholemeal flour as well as rye coarse meal for making gruel during the spring and autumn floods; it would also make groats. Kahala mill was one of four watermills of Kolga manor. The mill was brought to the museum in 1962 and opened for visitors in 1969."</item>
    	<item>"Sepa farm from Rõuge parish represents the household of a blacksmith in southern Estonia at the turn of the century. Brought to the museum in 1987–1997 and opened for visitors in 1999.\n\nThis small farm in Võru County had some 10 ha of poor soil, and smithcraft was the main source of income.\n\nDue to the changes in the economy of Estonia in the second half of the 19th century, rural handicraft developed at a fast pace. The amount of work for the village blacksmith from a long line of tradesmen also increased because farms started using better steel farming tools and machines. So the farm owners of Palometsa village who were interested in getting themselves a good blacksmith helped him set up Sepa farm by giving the logs for the buildings."</item>
    	<item>"Kalma windmill, ordered by Juhan Särk, was built by Mustvee mill builder Jakob Sõber in Kalma village, Torma parish. The former earned the money to build the mill by fishing in Lake Peipus. Kalma windmill is the museum exhibit of a Dutch type windmill which can be mainly recognised by the cap-like rotating roof with the sails. It was brought to the museum in 1972, rebuilt in 1991-1995."</item>
    	<item>"Ritsu farm is an example of a cotter’s household in southern Estonia. The barn-dwelling in the yard was built in 1860s on Ritsu farm in Tinnikuru village, Paistu parish. (The storehouse and the cattle-shed have not been built yet). It was brought to the museum in 1966, rebuilt in 1968–1975."</item>
    	<item>"Rusi farm from Võru County holds a special place in the museum display. All farmyard buildings except for the new storehouse were brought from Ala-Rusi farm in Pugritsa village, Karula parish, which has a strong connection with the history of Estonian art. Namely, this was the place where the famous sculptor Juhan Raudsepp (1896–1984) who was then known as Juku from Rusi grew up on the farm of his mother’s parents. Ala-Rusi was a farm with around 36 hectares of land and two horses, separated from the older large Mäe-Rusi farm for the family’s son upon his marriage. Ala-Rusi buildings were brought over in 1967, and the farmyard was opened for visitors in 2002."</item>
    	<item>"Will be opened in 2015!\n\nThe old farm Vanatalo was situated in Lõkova village (called Ojavere as a part of Estonia) in Pankjavitsa (later Vilo commune), which is now in the Pskov Oblast of Russian Federation.\n\nThe eastern part of Setomaa was characterised by farms that were fortified in a way: the dwelling was located in the centre of a so-called three-row yard with rows of outbuildings along two sides of the dwelling.  There were narrow yards closed with high gates between it and the outbuildings. The ends of all the buildings faced the village street.\n\nThe dwelling and the storehouse were brought to the museum in 1979."</item>
    	<item>"Will be opened in 2015!\n\nThe so-called Pechonkin’s house (by the owner’s surname) built in 1863 was brought from the town of Kallaste, former Kodavere parish.\n\nThe peculiar Russian settlement established on the shore of Lake Peipus was founded by Old Russian Believers who fled from Russia after the Orthodox Church dissent in the 18th century. The shore villages where soil was poor mainly lived off fishing, growing vegetables and, later, building work.\n\nThe dwelling was relocated in 1991."</item>
    	<item>"Jaagu farm was a homestead that was apportioned from a larger state manor to a soldier who had retired from the tsarist army. It had 9 hectares of land, of which 2 hectares was fields.\n\nSuch smallholders often earned their keep on the mainland doing seasonal labour, especially in construction. As well-regarded stonemasons, they erected buildings both on farms and manors and in the cities of Tallinn and Riga. They built their own buildings with love and care as well. In the winters, income was earned through handicrafts: women wove textiles, embroidered and sewed, while the men did logging and carpentry work.\n\nThe farm was opened at the museum in 1976."</item>
    	<item>"Jüri-Jaagu farm is an example of a 20th century tenant farm on Muhu Island. The buildings were brought to the museum from 1973-1985, and the farm was opened to visitors in 1996.\n\nMuhu farm had 34 hectares of land, of which 6 hectares were fields. As the stony soil and pastureland produced little income, the members of the large family earned money to pay the rent and other expenses from seasonal work.\n\nA ‘clean yard’ lies between the barn dwelling and the storehouse. Here fruit trees and flowers began to be planted in the 19th and 20th centuries. The cattle-shed and summer kitchen are in the cattle-yard, which leads to the village green."</item>
    	<item>"Kolga farm is an example of a Hiiumaa tenant farm and how it developed over time. The buildings are from Emmaste parish. The farm was opened to visitors in 1984. The role model for the typically spacious farmyard seen on Hiiumaa was Pendi farm in Lelu village, which still had the old fencing that partitioned the yard.\n\nMost Hiiumaa islanders lived less than 8 km from the coast, and thus they were seafarers and fishermen as well as farmers. Diversification was required to survive here, so they also engaged in woodworking for sale. Thanks to the location and the settlement history, Hiiumaa has been a cultural bridge between Estonia and Scandinavia."</item>
    	<item>"Roosta is an example of a western Saaremaa farm in a natural barter economy system dating from the serfdom era. It was brought to the museum from Kihelkonna and Mustjala parishes from 1965-1971, and opened to the public in 1972.\n\nAn average farm had around 45 hectares of land, of which about 5 hectares was stony fields. The estate owner had control of the farm family itself as well as the land and buildings and fishing rights in coastal waters.\n\nIn return for tenancy and a fishing license, the family had to perform corvee labour and pay a tithe in grain, hay, firewood, chickens and eggs and fish, among other products. If the men were away at sea, the women had to plough the fields.\n\nIn the mid-19th century, the islanders started to travel to the mainland to work as ditch diggers or construction workers."</item>
    	<item>"The Moravian Church prayer house was built in 1780 on Paka farm in Tuiu village, Mustjala parish. Brought to the museum in 1965. Such Moravian Church prayer houses started to be built around 1730, when the movement gained many followers.\n\nA simple building with Spartan furnishings and featuring a ‘black kitchen’ – uncommon in Estonia – reflects the tenets of the religious movement – humility, piety and belief in redemption through Christ´s sacrifice and belief in the resurrection.\n\nAt the centre of the edifice is the roovialune – a fireproof ‘black’ kitchen with stone walls and a clay-daubed pleached wicker ceiling. In the corner is an open hearth where the prayer room’s stoves were also stoked. The smoke is exhausted through a log chimney. This, a so-called Franck heating system, is seen in Estonian farm architecture only in western Saaremaa."</item>
    	<item>"This temporary residence was built in the late 19th century by Audru manor in Sarvi village in Audru parish for fishermen arriving from Hiiumaa for the Baltic herring catch. The building was brought to the museum in 1967, and erected in 1967-1968. The fishing house was torched by an arsonist on the day of the August putsch in 1991 and restored as a replica from 1991-1996."</item>
    	<item>"Until the end of the 19th century, common net fences for one or more villages were situated on the beaches. These were the net sheds for various boat crews. Nets and other fishing tackle were stored there. The seafront in the Open Air Museum’s island region features three net sheds from Saaremaa Island: Nasva, Toomalõuka and Alvi."</item>
    	<item>"In windy seaside areas lacking in rivers, post windmills ground grain for many generations. The entire body of the mill revolved atop a post. The small mills used on farms for single families were a sight unto themselves. They had parallels to a very ancient farm mill tradition in Scandinavia and southern Finland. Windmills were first mentioned in written documents in 14th century."</item>
    	<item>"Sutlepa chapel was built in the region populated by Estonian Swedes and is one of the oldest wooden buildings in Estonia. The chapel was built in Sutlepa village of Noarootsi parish as a subordinate church to Noarootsi parish church. The construction cannot be precisely dated: archival data mention the chapel as early as in 1627, but the year engraved above the church door is ‘1699’. The chapel was brought to the museum in 1970 and erected in 1971–1976. Sutlepa chapel was re-consecrated in 1989 and has since been a subordinate church of Jaani parish of the Estonian Evangelical Lutheran Church. Sermons are held in the chapel on major holy days and important dates of the folk calendar."</item>
    	<item>"Brought from Lau village of Juuru parish, Harju County. The shop building with rather a conventional floor plan was constructed in 1914 by Jaan Meiberg, a distiller from Ingliste manor. Brought to the museum in 1999 and opened for visitors in 2012.\n\nShops started emerging here and there in rural settlements in the last quarter of the 19th century when country population’s demand for bought-in goods increased. By the beginning of the 20th century the network of village shops had been established. Apparently the shop was there in the tsarist era, and it certainly operated from 1925 to 1940, when the Soviet rule was established. The museum display refers to 1938, the period when Estonia’s economy flourished. Visitors can travel back in time here, buying goods characteristic of that time in history."</item>
    	<item>"The fire station was built in 1928 in Orgmetsa village, Järva-Madise parish. It was brought to the museum in 1991. Such fire stations of medium size were built by rural firefighters’ societies in major Estonian villages in 1920s–1930s. Orgmetsa fire station belonged to the Aravete-Albu volunteer firefighters’ society founded in 1921. It was used to store manual fire engines with carts, barrels of water, fire hooks etc. Hoses could be dried   in the tower, where the fire bell was located as well. If necessary, firefighters could go to place up to 10 kilometres from the fire station."</item>
    	<item>"Kuie school was situated in Järva-Jaani parish, Kuie commune. The school building was completed in 1887. With the assistance of the founders of the Rocca al Mare school it was relocated and rebuilt in the museum in 1999, and the opening ceremony took place on 1 September 2000. From this day on it's been a home for museum's educational center.\n\After the commune reform of 1866, when decision-making rights concerning school life were given to farm owners, but manors were to provide the land and materials for building schools, numerous schools were built in Estonia. Kuie commune too felt that the old building constructed in 1842 was not enough anymore. On the territory of Kooli farm premises allocated by the manor (around 20 ha), the commune constructed rather a splendid school building.  The standard public facility design recommended in the Russian Empire was followed."</item>
    	<item>"Brought from Kolu village in Kose parish, Harju County. The inn with one stable located on the road from Tallinn to Tartu was built in 1840s. Brought to the museum in 1968. Nowadays it's a perfect place to rest one's feet and taste national dishes.\n\nManors started building inns on major roads as early as in Middle Ages. They would sell products of their own distilleries and offer night’s lodging and food to travellers. Farmers would listen to news brought by people passing through, engage in trade and hire workers. Most inns were closed down in 1900 after the state had established a monopoly on selling spirits."</item>
    </string-array>
    
    <array name="object_pictures">
        <item>@drawable/sassijaani</item>
        <item>@drawable/kostriaseme</item>
        <item>@drawable/nuki</item>
        <item>@drawable/natsi</item>
        <item>@drawable/harjapea</item>
        <item>@drawable/pulga</item>
        <item>@drawable/aarte</item>
        <item>@drawable/kahala</item>
        <item>@drawable/sepa</item>
        <item>@drawable/kalma</item>
        <item>@drawable/ritsu</item>
        <item>@drawable/rusi</item>
        <item>@drawable/setu</item>
        <item>@drawable/peipsivene</item>
        <item>@drawable/jaagu</item>
        <item>@drawable/jurijaagu</item>
        <item>@drawable/kolga</item>
        <item>@drawable/roosta</item>
        <item>@drawable/vennastekoguduse</item>
        <item>@drawable/hiidlasterandpuugi</item>
        <item>@drawable/vorgumajad</item>
        <item>@drawable/tuulikud</item>
        <item>@drawable/sutlepa</item>
        <item>@drawable/lau</item>
        <item>@drawable/orgmets</item>
        <item>@drawable/kuie</item>
        <item>@drawable/kolu</item>
    </array>
</resources>
